<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jerusalems vvatch-men, the Lords remembrancers: a sermon preached at the Abbie at VVestminster, before both Houses of Parliament, and the Assembly of Divines, upon their solemn fast, Iuly 7. 1643. / By Matth: Nevvcomen M.A. and Minister of the Gospell at Dedham in Essex. Published by order of both Houses of Parliament.</title>
            <author>Newcomen, Matthew, 1610?-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90064</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N911</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E63_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8797</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873404</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873404</idno>
            <idno type="VID">125874</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90064)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 125874)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 11:E63[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Jerusalems vvatch-men, the Lords remembrancers: a sermon preached at the Abbie at VVestminster, before both Houses of Parliament, and the Assembly of Divines, upon their solemn fast, Iuly 7. 1643. / By Matth: Nevvcomen M.A. and Minister of the Gospell at Dedham in Essex. Published by order of both Houses of Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Newcomen, Matthew, 1610?-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. F. for Christopher Meredith at the Crane in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an order to print on verso of first leaf.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon before the assembly of Lords, Commons, and Divines, upon their fast, Iuly 7. 1643.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah LXII, 6-7 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:125874:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>JERVSALEMS VVATCH-MEN, THE LORDS <hi>REMEMBRANCERS:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED at the Abbie at VVESTMINSTER, before both Houſes of <hi>Parliament, AND</hi> The Aſſembly of DIVINES, upon their <hi>Solemn Faſt, Iuly</hi> 7. 1643. BY MATTH: NEVV COMEN <hi>M. A.</hi> and Miniſter of the Goſpell at <hi>Dedham</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>As for me, I have not haſtned from being a Paſtour to follow thee, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have I deſired the wofull day, thou knoweſt: that which came out of my lips was right before thee.</p>
               <p>Be not a Terrour to me, thou art my hope in the day of evill,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 17.16, 17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Remember that I ſtood before thee to ſpeak good for them, and to turn away thy wrath from them,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jerem. 18.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Yee that have eſcaped the ſword, goe away, ſtand not ſtill. Remember the Lord afar off, and let <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> come into your minds,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 51.50.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Publiſhed by Order of both Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>M. F.</hi> for CHRISTOPHER MEREDITH at the Crane in Pauls Church-yard. 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:125874:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:125874:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE <hi>LORDS,</hi> The worthy Members of the HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOURABLE Houſe of COMMONS, <hi>AND</hi> The Learned and Religious DIVINES, now aſſembled to conſult about matters of <hi>RELIGION.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>Sermon</hi> might have been <hi>entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> from the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> and now from the <hi>Preſſe,</hi> as <hi>Pharez</hi> was from the <hi>womb,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 38.29.</note> with a, <hi>Quàm erupiſti, how haſt thou broken forth?</hi> were it not knowne to this <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> that the <hi>Parliament</hi> had deſigned another, both in <hi>yeares</hi> and <hi>all Intellectuall and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall abilities,</hi> far more fit for the <hi>ſolemn work</hi> of ſo <hi>ſolemne a day,</hi> in ſo <hi>ſolemne</hi> and <hi>Reverend an</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Conſiſting of both Houſes of Parliament &amp; the Divines all joyning in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation and prayer.</note> Aſſembly. But bodily infirmities compelling him with <hi>Zarah</hi> to <hi>draw back his hand,</hi> the work was (I know not by what providence) devolved on me, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. I was to that quire of <hi>Mourners</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſours,</hi> but as the graſhopper was to<note n="b" place="margin">Hujus memi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit &amp; Strabol. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; Clem. Al. in Protreptico al gentes, &amp; Phot. in Ep. ad Joen. Patrici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</note> 
               <hi>Eunomius</hi> his harp; <hi>quae Citharae jugo inſidens ruptae chordae ſonum expleret.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:125874:3"/>
            <p>The ſame <hi>Authority</hi> (which I am reſolved to obey, <hi>uſque ad Aras</hi>) that <hi>commanded</hi> mee to <hi>preach</hi> then, <hi>commands</hi> me now to make <hi>publique</hi> to the <hi>eyes of all,</hi> what <hi>then</hi> was committed <hi>to the ears of not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny;</hi> when the ſame <hi>Authority</hi> ſhall command other <hi>things</hi> that have ſince been ſpoken and <hi>tranſacted</hi> in your <hi>Aſſembly</hi> to ſee the <hi>Light,</hi> I doubt not but all ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-minded men, that have not been made drunk with the cup of Romes fornication, will acknowledge you have with a <hi>ſingle eye</hi> ſought <hi>Truth</hi> with <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>union</hi> with <hi>Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is (<hi>Men, Brethren</hi> and <hi>Fathers</hi>) a great work that <hi>God</hi> hath called you to ſet your heads, and hearts, and hands unto, to reſcue <hi>truth</hi> from the jaws of thoſe <hi>monſtrous errours,</hi> that had almoſt devoured it; to disburthen the worſhip of God of thoſe <hi>corruptions,</hi> that have ſo long clogged and defiled it; to adviſe of, and propound ſuch a Government in the Church, as may be moſt <hi>agreeable</hi> to Gods <hi>word,</hi> moſt conformed to the pattern in the <hi>Mount,</hi> and to the <hi>practiſes</hi> of the beſt <hi>Reformed Churches;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; Had our God caſt you upon this work in the moſt pacate <hi>times,</hi> and among a <hi>People</hi> the moſt prepared for <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> that ever any were, yet (in it ſelfe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) ſuch is the infinite weight of your <hi>employment</hi> as might even ſwallow up all your thoughts. But then to conſider how <hi>unprepared</hi> the hearts of <hi>people</hi> are for that which is the <hi>work</hi> of this <hi>age,</hi> and this <hi>Aſſembly, Reformation,</hi> which hath been repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People</hi> under the odious notion of <hi>Browniſme, Anabaptiſme, Church Anarchy,
<pb facs="tcp:125874:3"/>Confuſion;</hi> in ſo much that with many, <hi>endeavours</hi> and <hi>aſſays</hi> of Reformation will find no better entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> meſſengers of Reformation did, <hi>2 Chron. 30.10. when the people laughed them to ſcorn,</hi> and <hi>mocked them;</hi> Nay, with ſome worſe, for ſo enragedly doe ſome <hi>burn</hi> after their <hi>Idolatrous</hi> wayes, and ſo <hi>mad</hi> are they <hi>upon their own inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 50.38.</note> that deny them theſe, and it is to be feared you ſhall finde them in the temper the <hi>Abezrites</hi> were, ſcarce any thing will pacify them, but the bloud of thoſe that <hi>have caſt down the altar of</hi> Baal, <hi>and cut down the grove that was by it;</hi> Iudg. <hi>6.30.</hi> Doe not <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes</hi> cry already upon the <hi>diſuſe</hi> of ſome <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi> and the <hi>diſplacing</hi> of ſome Superſtitious <hi>Prieſts?</hi> do they not cry with <hi>Micah, Judg. 18.24.</hi> Yee have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away our Gods and our Prieſts, and what have we more? This makes the times ſo calamitous, as we may ſay of them with the Learned Rivet. <hi>In multis certè infoeliciſſima ſunt noſtra Tempora, in quibus in peſſum omnia ruunt, &amp; quaſi tranſverſum ire vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentur. Concutiuntur Regna, &amp; Reſpublicae; tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multibus omnia perſtrepunt, &amp; ſeditionibus; cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus terra polluitur; &amp; quod malum omnium malorum fons eſt, clamant peccata, et coelum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocant; profligatis ferè moribus honeſtis, &amp; vitiis latè quaſi apertâ portâ erumpentibus. Pruriunt ingenia multorum, &amp; in rebus Divinis ita ſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt &amp; adeò licenter, ut quod olim in populo E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braeo (quibus temporibus non erat Rex in Iſraele) quiſque quod rectum videbatur in oculis ſuis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciebant,</hi> Iud. <hi>17.6. Sic multi ſunt qui nullis repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis
<pb facs="tcp:125874:4"/>continentur, &amp; fidem in dies mutans, quam dum multiplicant, amittunt. Alios vetuſtâ ſocor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diâ detentos dum nullam mutationem admittunt in bonum, ita dementat ſuperſtitio, ut in monito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res inſurgant, ne dum ut eos patienter audiant.</hi> All this proclaims the work of <hi>Reformation</hi> the more <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary,</hi> but withall the more <hi>difficult.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againſt theſe <hi>difficulties</hi> what have you to <hi>encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage</hi> you? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: were yee encompaſſed as ſometimes <hi>Eliſha</hi> was, with an hoaſt of armed men, yet might yee ſay as he did there, <hi>They that be with us are more then they that be againſt us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For firſt,<note place="margin">Revel. 19 14.</note> with you are all the <hi>Armies in heaven:</hi> All the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Churches</hi> of Chriſt are with you, <hi>ſtriving with you by their prayers,</hi> (not only in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to <hi>your perſons,</hi> but to your <hi>employments</hi>) for protection, guidance, bleſsing. The appearing of Chriſt in the beauty of Reformation among us, may be ſaid to be <hi>the deſire of all</hi> (Chriſtian) <hi>Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, not only ſo, but yee have the prayers of thoſe that have been before us. For verily many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and righteous men have deſired to ſee the things which ye ſee,<note place="margin">Favour me the uſe of this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion by way of alluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> &amp; have not ſeen them; <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>Parliament</hi> reſolved upon a more thorough <hi>Reformation;</hi> an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly called to debate &amp; adviſe about the eſtabliſhing of Doctrine and worſhip, and the Government of the Church in a more pure &amp; regular manner; with how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tears and prayers did our Forefathers ſeek this at the hands of God? The firſt fruits of which prayers we (who are entred upon their labours) have already taſted, and ſhall reap in full anſwers, in due time if we faint not.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:125874:4"/>
            <p>Thirdly, you have the promiſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, Mat. <hi>18.20. Where two or three are met together in my Name, there am I in the middeſt of them.</hi> To be met together in the Name of Chriſt, implies <hi>3.</hi> things, <hi>1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Convenire ex vocatione.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Camero in Myrothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Convenire animo ſequendi praeſcriptum Dei. 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Ita ut unuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſque diffidat ſibi, &amp; ſoli Deo fidat.</hi> And if ever any in all theſe particulars were met together in the <hi>Name of Chriſt,</hi> then are you, and therefore may with a holy humble confidence challenge this promiſe of our Lord Ieſus, <hi>to be in the midſt among you:</hi> Chriſt being in the midſt of you, implies not only his <hi>adeſſe,</hi> but his <hi>praeeſſe</hi> too: as Pſalm <hi>82.1.</hi> And if God be thus with us, who can be againſt us? Rom. <hi>8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, ſome <hi>ſweet, encouraging, engaging</hi> experiences, we have had of the <hi>accompliſhment</hi> of this promiſe. He muſt have a heart more <hi>ignorant</hi> and <hi>unbeleeving</hi> then the <hi>Apoſtles Idiot,</hi> that ſhould come in and be an eare-witneſſe of your proceedings and not <hi>worſhip God and report</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>That God is in you of a truth.</hi> Verily I have often from my heart wiſhed that your <hi>greateſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries and Traducers</hi> might be witneſſes of your Learned, grave, pious <hi>debates,</hi> which were able to <hi>ſilence,</hi> if not <hi>convert Malignity it ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Goe on in this your might;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judges 6.14.</note> hath not the Lord ſent you? is not the Lord with you? <hi>goe on in this your might. Pergite quo coepiſtis pede.</hi> In that <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>wiſdome,</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>zeal for Truth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi> you have <hi>proceeded</hi> hitherto, <hi>goe on ſtill,</hi> to Love the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Peace.</hi> Peace is precious, and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:125874:5"/>is every grain and ſelvage of Gods truth. It was a ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Baſil. Mag. and it well reſembles him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>qui ſacris literis innutriti ſunt, ne unicam quidem ſyllabam Divinorum Dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum prodere ſuſtinent, ſed pro his omnia, ſi opus ſit, genera mortis libenter ſubeunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord ſtrengthen your <hi>hands</hi> and <hi>hearts</hi> unto the great <hi>work</hi> that lies before you, raiſe you above all diſcouragements and <hi>oppoſitions,</hi> fill you more and more with a Spirit of Wiſdome, diſcerning, Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, Courage, Zeale, faithfulneſſe; make you in this work of Reforming his Church as <hi>Zachariah</hi> and <hi>Haggai</hi> were inre-building the Temple, <hi>ut Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am hanc, quam inveniſtis minus quam Lateriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, reddatis pluſquam Marmoream:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suet. in vitâ Aug.</note> which is the ſincere deſire and prayer of him,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>who is Leſſe then the leaſt of all Gods mercies and Employments, MATTH. NEVVCOMEN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:125874:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Aſſembly of Lords, Commons, and Divines, <hi>upon their Faſt</hi> July 7. 1643.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſaiah 62. the latter part of the 6. and 7. ver.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Yee that make mention of the Lord keep not ſilence; And give him no reſt, till he eſtabliſh, and till hee make Ieruſalem a Praiſe in the earth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eholding the face of the <hi>Church</hi> in this Chapter,<note place="margin">The Chapt. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalyſed into 4. parts.</note> it appears to me as the <hi>Garden of God,</hi> made glad with <hi>four</hi> precious gracious <hi>promiſes,</hi> like the <hi>four Rivers</hi> that watered the Eden of the Lord.<note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In the firſt, the Lord <hi>promiſeth</hi> to <hi>raiſe</hi> his <hi>Church</hi> out of a low afflicted eſtate, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an illuſtrious glorious condition, <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>For Zions ſake I will not hold my peace, and for Ieruſalems ſake I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:125874:6"/>wil not reſt,</hi> (for ſo with a Learned Expoſitor, I take the words to be the words of <hi>God promiſing,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Soultetus ad loc:</note> &amp; not of the <hi>Prophet praying</hi>) <hi>For Zions ſake I will not hold my peace, &amp;c. untill the righteouſneſs therof go forth as brightneſſe, and the ſalvation of it as a Lampe that burneth;</hi> which <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> ſhall be ſo glorious that all the Kings and Nations of the earth ſhall behold and admire it, <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>It ſhall be as a crown of glory and a Royall Diademe in the hand of God, v.</hi> 3. And a <hi>new Name</hi> breathing nothing but delight and pleaſure will God put upon his Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Lord God delighteth in her,</hi> v. 4, 5.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In the ſecond place, the Lord <hi>promiſeth</hi> to raiſe up unto his Church <hi>Inſtruments</hi> fit for himſelfe to uſe in this great <hi>work of Reſtoring his Church</hi> and making it glorious, <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7. <hi>I have ſet watchmen upon thy walls O Ieruſalem, which ſhall not hold their peace night nor day, yee that are the Lords Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In the third, the Lord <hi>promiſeth</hi> to <hi>continue</hi> this his Churches felicity, and confirmes this <hi>promiſe</hi> with an <hi>Oath. The Lord hath ſworn by his Right hand and by the arm of his ſtrength, Surely, &amp;c. v.</hi> 8, 9.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> In the fourth, the Lord <hi>promiſeth</hi> an <hi>encreaſe</hi> and <hi>dilatation</hi> of his <hi>Church,</hi> by meanes of this proſperity and glory; <hi>Goe thorough, goe thorough the gates, prepare yee the way of the people, &amp;c. Lift up a Standard for the people, &amp;c.</hi> v. 10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>Our Text lies in the ſecond part of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wherein the Lord having <hi rend="sup">1</hi> 
               <hi>promiſed</hi> unto his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:125874:6"/>Church <hi>Inſtruments</hi> and means fit for himſelfe to uſe in the effecting of the great things before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed; <hi>I have ſet</hi> (for <hi>I will ſet,</hi> an uſuall Hebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme, thereby to ſhew the certainty of the thing promiſed) <hi>I have ſet watchmen upon thy wals O Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem:</hi> And having <hi rend="sup">2</hi> undertaken for the <hi>Fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and <hi>ſedulity</hi> of theſe <hi>watchmen, which ſhall never hold their peace night nor day:</hi> Preſently by an <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophe</hi> turnes to theſe watchmen, and gives them a charge to ſee they make good what he had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken: <hi>Yee that make mention of the Lord, keep not ſilence; give him no reſt, till he eſtabliſh, and till he make Ieruſalem a praiſe in the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words you may pleaſe to conſider theſe three things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">The text divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note>Firſt, the Perſons called upon, diſciphered thus, <hi>yee that make mention of the Lord.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, the ſervice or employment they are called unto, deſcribed Negatively; <hi>keep no ſilence, and give him no reſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thirdly, the Duration or extent of this em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment; <hi>till he eſtabliſh, and till he make Ieruſalem a praiſe in the earth.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe, <hi>the perſons called upon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Explained.</note> they are thus characteriſed, <hi>yee that make mention of the Lord;</hi> the margent reads it, <hi>yee that are the Lords Remembrancers;</hi> the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The Vulgar, <hi>qui Reminiſcimini Domini:</hi> Pagninus, <hi>qui Reminiſcimini Iehovae:</hi> Arias Montanus, <hi>Rememo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes Dominum:</hi> Jun. &amp; Trem. <hi>qui Commemoratis Iehovam.</hi> All which unleſſe it be our marginall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:125874:7"/>reading imply no other then what is the common duty and diſpoſition of all the people of God, to <hi>remember the Lord, and make mention of the Lord;</hi> only that; <hi>The Lords Remembrancers</hi> ſeems to have ſomething in it peculiar to ſome ranke and order of men; <hi>yee that are the Lords Remembrancers;</hi> yee to whom it doth <hi>ex officio</hi> belong to put the Lord in mind of his people and of his promiſes. In the Originall it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>C. à Lapide</hi> upon the place ſaith that the Kings of <hi>Iuda</hi> &amp; <hi>Perſia</hi> had <hi>ſuos</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">So 2 Sam. 8.16. Jehoſaphat the ſon of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilud <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; 2 Sam. 20.24. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Recorder, in the margent it is Remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer; <hi>qui negotia gerenda comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morat, &amp; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices por<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>git libellos.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Maskirim admonitores, qui ſingula geſta &amp; ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renda Regi in mentem revocarent;</hi> ſuch as we are wont to ſay are <hi>Regi à Commentariis.</hi> It ſeems this was ſome ſtanding office in the Court to be <hi>the Kings Remembrancer:</hi> to this the prophet here al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes, Yee that are <hi>the Lords Remembrancers;</hi> yee to whoſe <hi>office</hi> it belongs to put the Lord in mind of his Churches neceſſities, and his promiſes, which can be no other then the watchmen ſpoken of in the foregoing words, <hi>I have ſet watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men upon thy walls O Jeruſalem;</hi> therefore the Greek Tranſlation joyns theſe watchmen and this remembring the Lord in conſtruction together. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>And upon thy walls ô Ieruſalem I have ſet watchmen all the day, and all the night, which ſhall not hold their peace for ever remembring the Lord;</hi> ſo that the <hi>Lords Remembrancers</hi> here are the ſame with <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalems watchmen</hi> before, and they no other but the Prieſts and Prophets and Miniſters of the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:125874:7"/>
            <p>The ſecond thing conſiderable in the text is, the <hi>employment</hi> they are called to, and that is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed <hi>Negatively; keep no ſilence, give him no reſt;</hi> which implies that their <hi>employment</hi> here is <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,</hi> and that can be but either in <hi>preaching</hi> or in <hi>praying:</hi> Some think the Miniſters of the Lord are here called upon for diligence in both theſe; but in this place I conceive, the Lord calls them to attendance upon prayer, becauſe of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing words, <hi>give him no reſt.</hi> The pronoun there having reference to God, and not to Jeruſalem; keep no ſilence, give him, that is the Lord, no reſt, pray, cry importunately, unceſſantly. God here by his Prophet calls his Miniſters to pray, as elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where he doth, by his Apoſtle, to preach, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon;</hi> Night and day. <hi>I have ſet watchmen upon thy walls ô Ieruſalem, which ſhall not hold their peace night nor day; yee that are the Lords remembrancers, keep no ſilence, give him no reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third and laſt thing conſiderable in the words is, the <hi>Duration</hi> or <hi>Extent</hi> of this <hi>employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> how farre their prayer muſt extend it ſelfe, or how long they muſt continue praying, <hi>even till he eſtabliſh, and till he make Ieruſalem a praiſe,</hi> till <hi>God</hi> have not only <hi>laid the foundations,</hi> but <hi>ſet up the Pinacles</hi> of a <hi>glorious Church.</hi> Not only brought forth the <hi>Corner ſtone,</hi> but the <hi>Top ſtone of Ieruſalem, and all the earth with ſhouting, cry, Grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>grace to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might out of the words, preſent unto you ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:125874:8"/>Doctrines;<note place="margin">Severall Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines out of the text.</note> as many in number as the parts of the text: as,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that <hi>God will certainly eſtabliſh Ieruſalem, &amp; make it a praiſe in the earth.</hi> This is clear, for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly God would never call his ſervants to pray for that which he never intended to do; were there never a text but this in all the book of God, that told us of this beauty and glory, wherewith God in the latter dayes will clothe his Church, even upon <hi>earth;</hi> were there nothing ſaid of it elſewhere in this <hi>Evangelicall Prophet Iſaiah;</hi> nor any men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it in that <hi>Propheticall Evangeliſt</hi> St. <hi>Iohn,</hi> if in his whole book of Revelation, he had not uttered one word of this the Churches glory, yet in this one text, there is enough to ſupport the faith of Gods people, in the patient and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table expectation of it; God hath commanded prayer for it; therefore God will doe it: for, <hi>He never ſaith to the ſons of Iacob, Seek yee mee in vaine,</hi> Iſaiah 45.19.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>we might obſerve that, though the Lord will certainly make his Church glorious, a praiſe upon earth, yet he will not doe this till it be obtained of him by earneſt and unceſſant prayer:</hi> Therefore in order to his owne holy and bleſſed ends, he here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands his ſervants prayers.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly,<hi>we may obſerve this, that it is in ſpeciall manner the duty of Gods Miniſters to pray earneſtly and unceſſantly to God, that he would eſtabliſh and make Ieruſalem a praiſe in the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:125874:8"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Doctrine to be inſiſted upon,</note>This third I will embrace as adequately anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this Auditory and Day. To an <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of <hi>Gods Miniſters</hi> met together in a <hi>ſolemne Day of Prayer,</hi> to <hi>ſeeke God</hi> for the <hi>good</hi> of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> what can be more appoſite then ſuch a Doctrine as this that tels them, <hi>It is in a ſpeciall manner their Duty to pray,</hi> opportunè, importunè, <hi>unceſſantly, importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, that God would eſtabliſh and make Ieruſalem a praiſe in the earth?</hi> The God of wiſdome and grace who directed the thoughts of his Servant unto this word, enlarge his own gratious hand, and the heart and mouth of his poore and moſt unworthy inſtrument, that helped by his Spirit, and your Prayers, I may utter right things, and ſuch as may advance Gods glory, and further all our hearts, not onely in the worke of this day, but in that great employment whereunto wee deſire this day to ſanctifie our ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is in a ſpeciall manner the duty of Gods Miniſters to pray that God would eſtabliſh Ieruſalem and make it a praiſe in the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not ſay, it is needfull (in ſuch an Auditory, it cannot be;) but it may be convenient, and I muſt, <hi>pro more,</hi> a little open the termes of this propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Not to ſpeake of the <hi>perſons,</hi> upon whom this duty is impoſed, <hi>Gods Miniſters;</hi> nor of the <hi>duty impoſed</hi> upon them, <hi>Prayer;</hi> I ſhall onely ſpeake of the <hi>ſubject</hi> of the duty here propounded to us, which is two-fold:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Subjectum cui,</hi> or <hi>cujus;</hi> and <hi>Subjectum quod.</hi>
               <note place="margin">opened in two things.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt ſhewing <hi>whom wee muſt pray for;</hi> the ſecond, <hi>what we muſt pray for.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:125874:9"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Firſt for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we muſt pray.</note>For the firſt of theſe, the <hi>ſubjectum cui</hi> or <hi>cujus, whom we muſt pray for,</hi> the <hi>Text</hi> and <hi>Doctrine</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">Jeruſalem.</note> 
               <hi>Ieruſalem. Ieruſalem</hi> may be taken two wayes, either <hi>literally,</hi> or <hi>myſtically.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Literally, <hi rend="sup">1</hi> For the place and City ſo deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated, or <hi rend="sup">2</hi> For the people ſometime inhabiting that place. For the place or city, that was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſo famous among the Nations, the City where God dwelt, the habitation of his holineſſe, the place neere unto which <hi>Chriſt</hi> was borne, in which he converſed, manifeſted the truth of his godhead in his Actions, the truth of his manhood in his paſſions, was betrayed, ſcourged, reviled, condemned in it,<note place="margin">John 19.41.</note> crucified, buried neer unto it, this is <hi>literall Ieruſalem:</hi> but this is not that Ieruſalem we muſt pray for, our <hi>devotions</hi> muſt not with the <hi>Papiſts</hi> dote upon the <hi>ruines</hi> and <hi>rubbiſh</hi> of that bloudy citie, the City of Gods curſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Ieruſalem literally</hi> ſignifies the <hi>people</hi> of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the Nation of the Jews, whom God hath in his righteous indignation ſcattered over the face of the earth, as chaffe before the wind: theſe we may pray for, I meane <hi>the remnant accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the election of Grace,</hi> that God would ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them againe according <hi>to his promiſe: And ſo all Iſrael ſhall be ſaved,</hi> Rom. 11.26.</p>
            <p>But yet this is not <hi>that Ieruſalem</hi> here meant nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>The Ieruſalem</hi> meant in this place is the <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Ieruſalem,</hi> that <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> whereof this was but a type, the new<note n="*" place="margin">Revel. 21.2. which text ſeemes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre to this of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> &amp; ſpeak the ſame lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; for as here <hi>ver.</hi> 4.5. God ſaith, <hi>The Lan I ſhall be married;</hi> And, <hi>God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce over Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, as a bridegroome rejoyceth over his bride:</hi> ſo here <hi>John</hi> ſees this Ieruſalem <hi>prepared as a bride adorned for her husband</hi>
               </note> Ieruſalem comming downe from God out of Heaven: And ſo it implyes two things.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:125874:9"/>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>Church of God</hi> in the utmoſt latitude of it: the whole <hi>Catholique Church</hi> diſperſed over the world, <hi>the generall aſſembly and Church of the firſt borne is unto us Mount Sion, the City of the living God, the heavenly Ieruſalem,</hi> Heb. 12.22, 23. for which we are to pray, that God would <hi>eſtabliſh and make it a praiſe in the earth.</hi> And ſecondly, by <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem Myſticall</hi> we are to underſtand that <hi>particular Church,</hi> in which we live, of which we are, to which we ſtand in the ſame relation that the Iews did to Ieruſalem; for this we are to pray, that God would eſtabliſh, and make it a praiſe in the earth. And ſo I come to the ſecond thing to be explained,<note place="margin">Secondly, for what we muſt pray.</note> the <hi>ſubjectum quod,</hi> or, what it is we are to pray for.</p>
            <p>Two things we find mentioned in the text: firſt, that <hi>God would eſtabliſh:</hi> ſecondly, that <hi>God would make his Church a praiſe in the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Firſt, that God would eſtabliſh his Church.</note>Firſt, that <hi>God would eſtabliſh his Church;</hi> for though the Church hath a <hi>ſtrong foundation,</hi> and <hi>walles,</hi> and <hi>bulwarkes</hi> ſtrong, yet it is in it ſelfe but a weake building,<note place="margin">Mat. 16.18.</note> 
               <hi>earthly tabernacles</hi> planted on a <hi>rock.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 26 1. 2 Cor. 5.</note> That which God ſpeakes of the earth, may be applyed to the Church, Pſal. 75.3. <hi>The earth, and all the inhabitants of it are diſſolved, I beare up the Pillars of it.</hi> All the commiſſures and contig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of this great fabrick of the Univerſe would be looſned and disjoynted, if God did not put under his everlaſting armes, and beare up, and eſtabliſh the Pillars of it: So would it be in the Church of God; therefore we muſt pray, that God would eſtabliſh his Church,<note place="margin">In two things.</note> and that in two
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:125874:10"/>things: firſt <hi>in Truth;</hi> ſecondly, <hi>in Peace:</hi> Firſt, <hi>in truth againſt all errors;</hi> Secondly, <hi>in Peace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>, in Truth.</note>Firſt, we muſt pray that <hi>God would eſtabliſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his Church in truth.</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> is ſaid, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>to be the pillar and ground of truth;</hi> not as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts affirme, as if truth were grounded upon the judgement and determination of the Church: the Church is indeed the <hi>Pillar</hi> of <hi>truth,</hi> not becauſe it <hi>holds up</hi> the <hi>truth,</hi> but becauſe it <hi>holds forth</hi> the <hi>truth;</hi> the metaphor is taken, not from <hi>Pillars</hi> that are ſupporters of houſes, but from ſuch <hi>Pillars</hi> as anciently were wont to be fixed in market pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and other places of publique meeting, upon which they hung their lawes, (as the <hi>leges</hi> 12. <hi>Tabularum</hi> at Rome) that they might be publique to the view and notice of all men; as amongſt us <hi>Proclamations,</hi> for the ſame end are paſted upon poſts: ſuch a <hi>Pillar of truth</hi> we grant the Church is, and ought to be a Pillar to hold forth the truth, to the view of <hi>all men;</hi> a Pillar to which all men reſorting may read, and know the truth; it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Pillar and ground of truth;</hi> the word in the Originall is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which in the firſt and native ſignification is a ſeat; the <hi>Pillar and ſeat of truth,</hi> the place of truths abode and reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, its proper <hi>ubi,</hi> where truth is always to be found; this the <hi>Church</hi> of God is or ought to be.</p>
            <p>Now, though the <hi>Church</hi> of God ſhould be thus, yet we know there is no <hi>Church,</hi> but it is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto error: The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us there <hi>muſt be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:125874:10"/>Hereſies,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19. and that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> tells us, that there ſhall ariſe ſome ſuch ſubtill maſters of hereſie, that <hi>they ſhall ſeduce (if it were poſſible) the very elect of God, Mark</hi> 13.22. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt pray, that God would eſtabliſh his Church in truth againſt all errors.<note place="margin">Epheſ 6.14.</note> 
               <hi>Truth</hi> it is the <hi>Churches girdle;</hi> A Church <hi>quae hanc Zo na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perdidit aut ſoluta eſt,</hi> as the Latine proverb is, a <hi>Church</hi> that hath <hi>loſt</hi> this <hi>girdle of truth,</hi> or hath this <hi>girdle loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> is an <hi>Adulterous beggerly Church;</hi> therefore, <hi>yee that are the Lords Remembrancers keep no ſilence, give him no reſt till he eſtabliſh his Church in truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Secondly, in Peace.</note>And as in <hi>truth,</hi> ſo ſecondly, in <hi>Peace; Peace</hi> is one of the richeſt bleſſings of heaven, a <hi>compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive</hi> bleſſing, a <hi>circle of bleſſings;</hi> I will not <hi>rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toricate</hi> in the praiſes of it: the want of peace hath made us know what peace is worth; in the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this rich, deſirable bleſſing, we muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat the Lord to eſtabliſh <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> his <hi>Church; yee that are the Lords Remembrancers, keep no ſilence, give him no reſt, till he eſtabliſh Ieruſalem in peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this peace is threefold; <hi>Civill,</hi> with the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> with its own members; and <hi>ſpirituall</hi> or <hi>celeſtiall,</hi> with its head and God.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. Civill.</note> we muſt pray <hi>that God</hi> would eſtabliſh his <hi>Church in peace among the Nations;</hi> the Church of God is among the Nations,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.2.</note> as the <hi>lilly among the Thorns:</hi> the lot of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was among the uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed <hi>Heathens;</hi> ſo is the <hi>Churches;</hi> yet hath her God promiſed peace in the middeſt of enemies, <hi>Mic.</hi> 4.3. <hi>He ſhall judge among many people, and rebuke
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:125874:11"/>ſtrong Nations afar off, and they ſhall beat their ſwords into ploughſhares, and their ſpears into pruning hooks, Nation ſhall not lift up a ſword againſt Nation, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall they learn war any more, but they ſhall ſit every man under his vine, and under his figtree, and none ſhall make them afraid: for the mouth of the Lord of Hoaſts hath ſpoken it;</hi> You that are the Lords Remembrancers, keep no ſilence, give him no reſt, till he eſtabliſh his Church in this peace.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is peace <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> peace of the Church with its own members,<note place="margin">Secondly, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall.</note> peace in the bowels and boſome of the Church; wee muſt pray, that God would eſtabliſh his Church in that; that the Church may not languiſh, and die of <hi>Antiochus</hi> his diſeaſe, a torment in her bowels, that there may be no <hi>incompoſable diviſions,</hi> no <hi>irreconciliable rents,</hi> no <hi>in urable ruptures</hi> in the Church, which is one of the greateſt and ſaddeſt miſchiefs, and miſeries can fall upon the <hi>Church,</hi> or the <hi>Church</hi> fall under: That <hi>God</hi> who makes <hi>men to be of one minde in a houſe,</hi> as the greek reads that of the 68. Pſalme, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that God I ſay can make men of one mind, in a <hi>Church,</hi> in a <hi>Nation,</hi> in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed that he will doe it, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.19. <hi>I will give them one heart,</hi> and <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.6. <hi>I will turn to the people a pure language, that they may all call upon the name of the Lord to ſerve him with one conſent.</hi> O happy, happy we, if God would fulfill theſe promiſes in us! happy we, if we could obtain this at the hands of God by our prayers! <hi>yee that are the Lords Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancers,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:125874:11"/>keep no ſilence, give him no reſt, till he eſtabliſh his Church in this peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Thirdly, Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall or Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall.</note>Thirdly, there is <hi>ſpirituall</hi> or <hi>celeſtiall</hi> peace, peace between <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Church;</hi> wee muſt pray that <hi>God</hi> would eſtabliſh his <hi>Church</hi> in that alſo, that <hi>God</hi> would ſo watch over, and work in his <hi>Church,</hi> that no ſin may take hold and ſpread upon it, which might cauſe a quarrell between his <hi>Church</hi> and him, or cauſe the Lord to ſay, <hi>Mine heritage is to me as a ſpeckled bird,</hi> Ier. 12.9. That God would ſo order all the wayes of his Church before him, and towards him, that he may never know her by any other then thoſe precious and lovefull names of <hi>Ammi</hi> and <hi>Ruhamah, Hephzibah</hi> and <hi>Beulah: Yee that are the Lords Remembrancers, keep no ſilence, give him no reſt till he eſtabliſh Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem his Church in this peace alſo.</hi> Thus you ſee the firſt thing we are to pray for, that God would eſtabliſh his <hi>Church</hi> upon <hi>the two pillars</hi> of <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>peace,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> did the proch of the Temple upon thoſe two brazen pillars <hi>Iachin</hi> and <hi>Boaz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond thing we muſt pray for, That God would make his Church a praiſe.</note>Yet there is one thing more, that this Text commands us to pray for, that is, that <hi>God would make Ieruſalem a praiſe; Yee that are the Lords Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancers, keep no ſilence, give him no reſt, til hee eſtabliſh, and till he make Ieruſalem a praiſe in the earth.</hi> In the <hi>former</hi> we pray that God would <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie</hi> his <hi>Church,</hi> in this, that <hi>God would beautify</hi> his <hi>Church;</hi> make it <hi>cleare as the morning, faire as the moon, glorious as the ſun, terrible as an army with banners, lovely as Tirzah, comely as Ieruſalem, the praiſe of all the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:125874:12"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">This God doth by five things.</note>Now God makes his <hi>Church a praiſe in the earth,</hi> ſpecially by theſe five things;</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, by furniſhing his Church with fulneſſe of ordinances.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, by ruling his Church according to his own orders.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, by filling his Church with abundance of light and knowledge.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, by improving this knowledge to the working of holineſſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, by enlarging and encreaſing his Church by theſe meanes.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Firſt, by fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing it with ordinances.</note>Firſt, God makes his Church a <hi>praiſe in the earth, by furniſhing it with fulneſſe of ordinances:</hi> this was that which was the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle calls it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. the preheminency of the Church of the Iewes above all other Nations, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, firſt of all and chiefly, it was this, <hi>that to them were committed the oracles of God;</hi> this is that which God himſelf tells his people, ſhould make them glorious and praiſe-worthy in the eyes of all the Nations of the world, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.6, 7, 8. <hi>This is your wiſdome and your underſtanding, in the ſight of the Nations, which ſhall hear all theſe ſtatutes, and ſay, Surely this Nation is a wiſe &amp; underſtanding peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: for what Nation is there ſo great, who hath God ſo nigh unto them, as the Lord our God is in all things, that we call upon him for? And what Nation is there ſo great, that hath ſtatutes and judgements ſo righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as all this law, that I ſet before you this day?</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:125874:12"/>Now when God beſtowes his oracles and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances upon a people, firſt his <hi>word,</hi> and then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending ordinances, <hi>ſeales, Sabbaths, cenſures, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred in purity,</hi> and in <hi>power,</hi> then he makes them a <hi>praiſe: Yee that are the Lords Remembrancers, keep no ſilence, give him no reſt, til he thus make his Church a praiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. By ruling it according to his own orders.</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> makes his <hi>Church a praiſe by ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it according to his own order:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, are the two great deſtroyers of the Church of God; it is equally prejudiciall to the <hi>Church, not to be ordered at all, as to be ordered after the luſts &amp; wils of men;</hi> God (who is the God of order, &amp; <hi>not</hi> the <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of confuſion, but of peace, as in all the Churches of the</hi> Saints, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33.) would have all things in all Churches, <hi>be done decently and in order, v.</hi> 40. now when <hi>all ordinances</hi> and <hi>offices</hi> are adminiſtred in the <hi>Church</hi> according <hi>as God hath ordered,</hi> then is that <hi>Church a praiſe in heaven and earth,</hi> with <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Saints.</hi> 1 Cor. 11.2. <hi>Now I praiſe you brethren that you remember me in all things, and keep the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances as I delivered them unto you.</hi> And on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide diſorder or deflection from the rule of Chriſt, though but in <hi>one</hi> adminiſtration, is a ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh and doth detract from the Churches praiſe, as appears in the ſame chepter, v. 17. <hi>Now in this that I declare unto you, I praiſe you not, that you come together not for the better, but for the worſe;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 22. <hi>What, have you not houſes to eat and to drink in? or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe you the Church of God, and ſhame them that have not? what ſhall I ſay to you? ſhall</hi> I praiſe you <hi>in this?</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:125874:13"/>I praiſe <hi>you not; one</hi> aberration from the rule of Chriſt in the adminiſtration of this <hi>one</hi> ordinance of the ſupper of the Lord, caſts a <hi>cloud</hi> upon this <hi>Churches glory,</hi> and cauſes a great diminution of their praiſe, therefore we muſt pray that God would help his Church in all things to <hi>keep the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances as they are delivered unto us: Yee that are the Lords Remembrancers, keep no ſilence, give him no reſt, til he make his Church thus a praiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. By filling it with abundance of light and knowledge.</note> God makes his Church a praiſe <hi>when he fills it with abundance of light and knowledge;</hi> when after a <hi>night</hi> of ignorance or error that had ſwallowed up, and buried the <hi>Church</hi> of God, the <hi>Church</hi> hath a <hi>reſurrection, and looks forth as the morning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>cleare as the ſun, faire as the moon,</hi> it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſheth all eyes, and fixeth them upon it ſelfe in admiration, that men ſay, <hi>Who is this that locketh forth as the morning? Cant.</hi> 6.10. Yee that are the Lords <hi>Remembrancers, keep no ſilence, give him no reſt, til he make Ieruſalem thus a praiſe;</hi> remember him of that which he hath promiſed, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 11.9. <hi>All the earth ſhall be filled with the knowledge of the Lord, as the waters cover the ſea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">4. By improving this light to the working of holineſſe.</note> God makes his Church a praiſe, <hi>by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving &amp; ſanctifying this knowledge, to the working of holineſſe in the hearts and lives of his people;</hi> this was the praiſe of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> it was a <hi>holy City,</hi> this is the <hi>praiſe</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> they are a <hi>holy people, Deut.</hi> 26.18, 19. <hi>The Lord hath avouched thee this day, to be his peculiar people, as he hath promiſed thee, and that thou ſhouldeſt keep all his Commandements:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:125874:13"/>and to make thee high above all Nations which he hath made,</hi> and that <hi>thou maieſt be an holy people</hi> unto the Lord thy God <hi>as he hath ſpoken.</hi> Abundance of <hi>light unſanctifyed</hi> would make the <hi>Church,</hi> if it were poſſible, rather <hi>hell</hi> then <hi>heaven,</hi> and make <hi>men</hi> but like the <hi>devills,</hi> who know much, but are the more deſperately wicked, therefore we muſt pray that <hi>God</hi> would <hi>ſanctify</hi> that <hi>knowledge,</hi> wherewith he filleth his <hi>Church,</hi> that ſo the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thereof may be perfect: <hi>Yee that are the Lords Remembrancers, keep no ſilence, give him noreſt, till he make Ieruſalem thus a praiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, God makes his Church a praiſe,<note place="margin">5. By encreaſing his Church.</note> 
               <hi>by encreaſing his Church, by enlarging the tents, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the cords of it;</hi> this is a bleſſing God calls his Church to rejoyce in, <hi>Eſay</hi> 51.1, 2, 3. <hi>Sing O barren, &amp;c. break forth into ſinging, &amp;c. enlarge the place of thy tent, and let them ſtretch forth the curtains of thine habitations, ſpare not, lengthen thy cords, and ſtrengthen thy ſtakes, for thou ſhalt break forth on the right hand, and on the left: and thy ſeed ſhall inherite the Gentiles, and make the deſolate Cities to be inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> We are to pray that God would make his Church a praiſe thus alſo.</p>
            <p>Thus you have, <hi>(Right Honourable, Honourable, Reverent, and beloved in our Lord Ieſus)</hi> the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of this <hi>doctrine</hi> as fully as my weak thoughts in the little time I had to beſtow upon this work were able to comprehend it; yee ſee <hi>for whom we are to pray, Ieruſalem,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of God in <hi>generall,</hi> &amp; our own in <hi>particular;</hi> yee ſee <hi>what it is we are to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:125874:14"/>deſire</hi> for the one &amp; for the other, <hi>truth, peace, and praiſe;</hi> ſuch a <hi>trinity</hi> of <hi>bleſsings,</hi> as the <hi>bleſſed Trinity</hi> hath none better to beſtow upon the <hi>dearly beloved of his ſoul,</hi> while ſhe ſojourns upon earth. I know I ſpeak to an Auditory ſo <hi>rationall</hi> as I ſhal not need <hi>confirm</hi> this <hi>truth</hi> by <hi>reaſons;</hi> &amp; to <hi>ſo cordiall</hi> to the <hi>Church of</hi> God, as I ſhall as little need to ſtir you up to the practice of this truth by application;<note place="margin">The point con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</note> elſe I might fill up a large portion of the time remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in telling you how <hi>all the Lords remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in all</hi> the ages of the Church, under <hi>the Law, under the Goſpell,</hi> have exemplified this truth: <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law,</hi> before the Captivity, <hi>Moſes, Samuel, David, Iſaiah, Ieremy,</hi> which of the Lords Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets have not made the <hi>eſtabliſhing</hi> and beautify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> the burthen of their prayers? In the <hi>captivity</hi> though they had loſt their <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> and the <hi>fire</hi> of the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> that came from heaven, yet they had not loſt this holy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly diſpoſition, of <hi>praying</hi> for <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant evidence of it, in <hi>Ezekiel, Daniel, Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai;</hi> and after the captivity, in <hi>Ezra, Nehemiah,</hi> and <hi>others;</hi> And now in the times of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> the ſame ſpirit ſtill animates <hi>Gods children,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines their hearts ſtill to ſeek the good of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem;</hi> how doe the Apoſtles in ſeverall Epiſtles te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify this diſpoſition in them? <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.9. <hi>God is my witneſſe whom I ſerve with my ſpirit in the Goſpel of his Son, that without ceaſing I make mention of you</hi> (ſaith that Apoſtle to the Church of Rome) <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in my prayers;</hi> ſo <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.16, 17. <hi>making men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:125874:14"/>of you in my prayers, that the God of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the Father of glory, may give unto you, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, ſo much religion have the Saints of God before us placed in this duty of praying for <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> that they have <hi>deprecated</hi> the neglect of this as a moſt abominable ſinne: 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.23. <hi>As for mee, God forbid that I ſhould ſinne againſt you, in cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to pray for you;</hi> nay, have <hi>imprecated</hi> a curſe u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon themſelves, if ever they ſhould be ſo wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.5, 6. <hi>If I forget thee O Ieruſalem, let my right hand forget her cunning: if I doe not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thee, let my tongue cleave to the roofe of my mouth, if I prefer not Ieruſalem above my chiefe joy;</hi> it is one of the greateſt judgements that can befall a Prophet, to be ſilenced: witneſſe <hi>Zachary</hi> whoſe unbeleef God puniſhed with this, as an <hi>only judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> witneſſe thoſe amongſt our ſelves, that have had their mouths ſtopped by the violent hand of man, who know what it is to have the word of God as a fire in their bones and no vent for it; yet even to <hi>this,</hi> doth the <hi>Prophet</hi> here curſe himſelfe, <hi>If I forget thee O Ieruſalem,</hi> if I doe not remember to <hi>mourn</hi> for <hi>thee,</hi> to <hi>pray</hi> for <hi>thee,</hi> let me <hi>never pray</hi> more, let mee <hi>never ſpeak more if I forget to ſpeak for thee, let my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth;</hi> The good Lord be mercifull to every one of us, and pardon all our forgetfulneſſe of Ieruſalem, whom we have as much cauſe and reaſon to remember as ever any had.<note place="margin">Proved by Reaſons.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For 1 is not <hi>Ieruſalem</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 12.22.</note> the <hi>city of God,</hi> the<note n="b" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>houſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:125874:15"/>of God,</hi> the<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 135.4. Titus 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>peculiar of God,</hi> the<note n="d" place="margin">Iſaiah 62.4.</note> 
               <hi>delight of God,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Iſay 62.2.</note> 
               <hi>the crown of glory,</hi> the <hi>royall diadem</hi> in the hand of God? is not<note n="f" place="margin">Cant. 5.2.</note> the <hi>Love,</hi> the <hi>dove,</hi> the <hi>Spouſe,</hi> the <hi>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Eph 1.23.</note> the <hi>body,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Eph 1.23.</note> the <hi>fulneſſe,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">2 Cor. 8.23.</note> the <hi>glory of Ieſus Chriſt?</hi> and in all theſe reſpects doth it not deſerve our prayers?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And ſecondly, are not earth and hell up in armes againſt Ieruſalem? are not men and devils in league together, to confound and deſtroy Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem? <hi>Pſalm</hi> 83.3, 4. <hi>They have taken crafty coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell againſt thy people, and conſulted againſt thy hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ones. They have ſaid, Come, and let us cut them off from being a Nation: that the name of Iſrael may be no more in remembrance. Geball, and Ammon, and Amalek, &amp;c.</hi> And doth not Ieruſalem in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect now need our prayers?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And thirdly, hath not the Lord made promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes unto Ieruſalem of theſe things we are to pray for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of <hi>truth and peace,</hi> Ierem. 33.6. <hi>I will cure them, and reveal abundance of truth and peace unto them:</hi> as alſo <hi>of praiſe,</hi> v. 9. <hi>It ſhall be to me a name of joy, a praiſe and an honour before all the Nations of the earth;</hi> and <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.20. <hi>I will make you a name and a praiſe among all the people of the earth.</hi> And is not the Lord able to accompliſh theſe promiſes not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding al their counter-machinations of his enemies? <hi>Iſay</hi> 46.10. <hi>My counſell ſhall ſtand, and I will doe all my pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Yet fourthly, It is not the Lords pleaſure to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh theſe things unto his Church but in and by his peoples prayers; <hi>Ierem.</hi> 33.3. <hi>Call unto mee
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:125874:15"/>and I will anſwer thee, and ſhew thee great and mighty things which thou knoweſt not; Ezek.</hi> 36.37. <hi>I will yet for this be enquired of by the houſe of Iſrael to doe it for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Doctrine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed,</note>
               <hi>Sed quò feror?</hi> ſome uſe I would gladly make of this point, if I knew what; I might afford vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of profitable inſtructions, but it is not for me to preſume to inſtruct ſo <hi>Honourable, Learned</hi> and <hi>Religious</hi> an Aſſembly; give me leave to apologize for my ſelfe with <hi>Elihu, Iob.</hi> 32.6. <hi>I ſaid I am of few days, and yee are old, wherefore I was afraid and durſt not ſhew you mine opinion; I ſaid dayes ſhould ſpeak, and multitudes of yeares ſhould teach wiſdome.</hi> The Lord knows, glad would I have been to ſit at any of your feet to learn, rather then to ſtand hereto teach, and to receive rather then to give inſtruction, therefore I decline that work.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">For Reproof.</note>In the next place, this truth might ſerve for reproofe, and if ſuch an application would not lead me beſides my Auditory, ô with what vehemency might a man from hence, in <hi>the name and by the Spirit of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt</hi> thunder indignation and wrath upon the heads of thoſe, who though they have uſurped, and poſſeſſed the place of ſuch as <hi>ſhould</hi> be the <hi>Lords Remembrancers,</hi> yet in ſtead of performing the duty of this text have practiſed the cleane contrary, in ſtead of praying that God would <hi>eſtabliſh his Church in truth,</hi> have endevored nothing but <hi>to undermine the truth,</hi> to ſubvert, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterate the truth; their <hi>folly</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeakes, 2 Tim. 3.9.) <hi>is manifeſt unto all men,</hi> God
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:125874:16"/>hath unmasked them, and all that will ſee may ſee their deſigne was to let in ſuch an inundation of <hi>popery</hi> and <hi>Socinianiſme</hi> as ſhould have drowned the truth of God for ever; in ſtead of <hi>praying</hi> that God would <hi>eſtabliſh his Church in peace,</hi> they have acted the part of thoſe unclean ſpirits, the <hi>frogs ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi> of, Rev. 16.14. ſtirring up the <hi>kings of the earth to battle againſt the Church of God;</hi> firſt in <hi>Scotland,</hi> who were the Incendiaries, what the fuell of the war there? And ſince that in <hi>England,</hi> have not the warres of both kingdomes had the ſame fuell and fomenters? and who are they but the <hi>Ieſuitizing clergie of England,</hi> who like the uncleane ſpirit we reade of <hi>Mark</hi> 9. fearing they ſhall now be caſt out of their long poſſeſſion, <hi>rent</hi> and <hi>tear</hi> the kingdom, and lay it wallowing (not as he did the child there, in its foam, but) in its bloud? What ſhall I ſpeake of ſuch a clergie? who in ſtead <hi>of praying</hi> that God would make his Church a praiſe, have endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red nothing more then to <hi>rob</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of all that might make it praiſe-worthy, in ſtead of deſiring that the <hi>Church might enjoy fulneſſe of ordinances,</hi> endeavouring to <hi>ſtrip the Church</hi> of them all; to <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh Sabbaths,</hi> to bring the <hi>delight of dayes,</hi> the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>dayes</hi> under the curſe of <hi>Iobs</hi> birth day, <hi>Let it not be joyned to the days of the year, let it not come into the number of the months;</hi> to <hi>excommunicate prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching</hi> and <hi>praying,</hi> and caſt them quite out of the Church; to <hi>turn</hi> the <hi>ſacrament of the Lords ſupper</hi> into a <hi>ſacrifice of the altar;</hi> In ſtead of praying that all <hi>ordinances</hi> and <hi>offices</hi> might be adminiſtred ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:125874:16"/>to <hi>Chriſts rule and order,</hi> would have <hi>all things</hi> in Gods houſe &amp; worſhip <hi>done</hi> according to their own <hi>fancy, will, luſt, humour.</hi> What ſhal we ſay to ſuch a <hi>Clergy?</hi> (they dote upon the name ſtill,<note place="margin">Ariſt. de Hiſt. Anim. l. 8. c. 27.</note> let them enjoy it) <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſpeaks of a little worm cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is peſtilently noxious &amp; deſtructive to Bee-hives; no leſſe noxious and deſtructive hath our <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>greateſt part of them</hi> been to the true Church of God amongſt us; againſt whom, the Church of God may powre out as ſad complaints to her Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> as ſometimes ſhe did, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. <hi>The watchmen, the keepers of the wall, found me, they ſmote me, they took away my vaile:</hi> let ſuch read their doom, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2 <hi>their judgement now of a long time lingreth not, &amp; their damnation ſleepeth not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I had not turned aſide to this reproofe, (for I look for none of this generation here this day) had it not been to provoke my ſelfe and you to a more ſerious and deep humiliation for thoſe abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of the late times, which though many of us have ſeen and obſerved even then, and ſome of us have felt and ſmarted under the violences thereof, yet few I fear amongſt us have had our hearts ſo humbled for the iniquity of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as they ſhould have beene: the Lord help us ſo to take to heart this day, our own and other mens ſins, <hi>that he may forgive our iniquities, and heal our Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I return to my Auditory, and the only bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe I ſhall aſſume, <hi>brethren</hi> and <hi>fathers,</hi> is but to do as much as <hi>Naamans</hi> ſervant did unto his Lord, exhort you to doe that which you know God
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:125874:17"/>would have you doe, pray for Ieruſalem: and I am confident I might ſpare even this; it is your work daily; but God having called me this day to ſpeak unto you, for <hi>Zions</hi> ſake I cannot hold my peace; <hi>Qui monet ut facias quod facis, dum monet lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Doctrine applyed for exhortation,</note>
               <hi>Is it the duty of Miniſters in a ſpeciall manner to pray unceſſantly that God would eſtabliſh Ieruſalem and make it a praiſe in the earth?</hi> then let every one of us by ſolemn engagements to God &amp; to his Church bind our ſelves to the performance of this duty: and ſurely brethren if ever there were <hi>times</hi> that <hi>called</hi> for this <hi>duty,</hi> if ever there were <hi>men called</hi> to this <hi>duty, this</hi> is the <hi>time, we</hi> are the <hi>Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. Enforced from the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</note> for the <hi>time;</hi> if ever there were time that did command the moſt importune and unceſſant prayers of all Gods miniſters and people, (for here I will take in all) that they ſhould cry mightily to the Lord night and day in the behalf of Ieruſalem, <hi>keep no ſilence, give him no reſt, til he eſtabliſh and make Ieruſalem a praiſe in the earth,</hi> if ever there <hi>were</hi> a time that did exact this, <hi>Now</hi> is the <hi>time.</hi> Had I art or grace enough to preſent before you the <hi>lively</hi> (or rather) <hi>gaſtly deadly</hi> face of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> the <hi>Churches of Chriſt Ieſus</hi> at this time, I know it would command tears and prayers from the moſt flinty heart in this congregation: could I let you ſee <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> like that man in the parable, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.30. that went down from <hi>Ieruſalem, fallen among theeves, and by them ſtripped and wounded and left halfe dead,</hi> while many, too many with the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:125874:17"/>
               <hi>Prieſt and Levite</hi> paſſe by on the other ſide of the way, and will not ſee (though they cannot but ſee) the Churches bleeding miſeries; <hi>amongſt all her lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers there is none to comfort her, Lam.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Zion ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth forth her hands, and there is none to comfort her, Lament.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Zion</hi> ſpreadeth forth her hands from ſea to ſea, from one Nation to another peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and there is none to comfort her, <hi>there is none to guide her amongſt all the ſons whom ſhe hath brought forth, neither is there any that takes her by the hand of all the ſons that ſhe hath brought up, Eſay</hi> 51.18. O were I able to expreſſe this to the life unto you, you would ſay, if ever there were a time for you to ſhew your ſelves as the <hi>good Samaritane</hi> to beſtow, as he did, your <hi>wine,</hi> your <hi>oyle,</hi> your <hi>money,</hi> nay your <hi>teares,</hi> your <hi>prayers,</hi> your <hi>blouds</hi> upon the healing of the Churches wounds, <hi>Now</hi> is the <hi>time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or could I let you ſee the <hi>Church Ieruſalem,</hi> as <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw her in that Revelation which was given unto him by Chriſt Ieſus, chap. 12. in the <hi>ſame condition,</hi> though not in the <hi>ſame cloathing;</hi> a <hi>woman cloathed, not</hi> (as there) <hi>with the ſun,</hi> but with a <hi>cloud, not</hi> having the <hi>moon</hi> under <hi>her feet,</hi> but a <hi>globe of flames,</hi> a <hi>field of blood under her feet,</hi> not as there with a <hi>crown of twelve ſtarres upon her head,</hi> but rather in <hi>Tamars</hi> dreſſe and poſture, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.19. who with <hi>aſhes on her head,</hi> and her <hi>garment of divers colours</hi> (the enſigne of her Virginity and Royalty) <hi>rent and torne,</hi> and with <hi>her hands upon her head going forth</hi> crying, ſuch may we conceive the dreſſe and poſture of the <hi>Church of Chriſt</hi> to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:125874:18"/>be, ſhe now, as there, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12. <hi>cryeth travelling and pained to be delivered;</hi> in this pained condition the Church hath been now almoſt theſe three years, ever ſince the beginning of this Parliament, the Church of God amongſt us hath been in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, crying and pained to be delivered; and all this while, as there, the <hi>great red dragon ſtands before the woman to devour the child as ſoone as it is born.</hi> O! the ſight of the Church in ſuch a ſad conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might force a <hi>teare from a ſtone,</hi> a <hi>prayer</hi> from a <hi>ſpeechleſſe, heartleſſe man;</hi> but from <hi>Miniſters,</hi> from thoſe <hi>that are the Lords Remembrancers,</hi> me thinks it might <hi>draw tears enough to rince</hi> the <hi>earth</hi> from <hi>bloud,</hi> and <hi>prayers enough</hi> to offer <hi>violence</hi> to <hi>heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But not to ſpeak parabolically, but plainly, <hi>I ſay again, if ever there were a time</hi> that did command the moſt importune and unceſſant prayers of all Gods miniſters and people, <hi>now</hi> is the <hi>time;</hi> was there ever <hi>time,</hi> wherein the <hi>Church</hi> of God was more ſhaken, more in danger to have <hi>both</hi> her <hi>pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars</hi> of <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> broken, reduced to <hi>duſt,</hi> to <hi>nothing,</hi> then at this time? The enemies of the Church have a long time ſought to <hi>undermine</hi> the <hi>truth,</hi> but now, they <hi>raiſe Armes againſt the truth,</hi> they <hi>plant open battery</hi> againſt the <hi>truth.</hi> And for our <hi>peace,</hi> where is it? <hi>Terras reliquit,</hi> it hath taken to it ſelf the <hi>wings</hi> of <hi>a dove,</hi> and forſaking earth is fled to <hi>heaven,</hi> frighted he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with the <hi>ſound</hi> of the <hi>trumpet,</hi> the <hi>alarum</hi> of <hi>warre,</hi> and the <hi>cryes</hi> of <hi>bloud.</hi> We may <hi>chronicle</hi> of our age, that which the Prophet <hi>Azariah</hi> ſpake of ſome ages of Iſrael,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:125874:18"/>2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.5, 6. <hi>In thoſe times there was no peace to him that went out, nor to him that came in, but great vexations were upon all the inhabitants of the countries. And Nation was deſtroyed of Nation, and city of city: for God did vex them with all adverſity.</hi> Never was this poor Church &amp; people in a more broken diſtreſſed condition in regard of <hi>peace ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill,</hi> nor ſcarce ever worſe in regard of peace ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall: now when there are ſo many <hi>ſwords</hi> in <hi>England</hi> and in <hi>Ireland</hi> drawn againſt the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants;</hi> ô that <hi>we</hi> ſhould be even at <hi>daggers draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> one againſt another! O the bitter <hi>diviſions</hi> and <hi>digladiations</hi> of Proteſtants amongſt themſelves in theſe bleeding times! <hi>For the diviſions of Reuben there are great ſearchings of heart; for the diviſions of Reuben there are great ſearchings of heart.</hi> Holy <hi>Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> and <hi>Hooper,</hi> though in the times of the <hi>peace</hi> &amp; <hi>liberty</hi> of the goſpell, they could never agree a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout black and white, but had many wrathfull bickerings, yet in time of <hi>perſecution</hi> for the <hi>goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> they could, as their own expreſſion is, agree in red; when God came to put them together in tears, and ſufferings, and bloud, they could forget all differences of judgement then, and <hi>love</hi> and <hi>live</hi> and <hi>die</hi> together as brethren. Doe thoſe know <hi>what ſpirit they are of,</hi> that at ſuch a time as this, when all the true hearted Proteſtants in <hi>England</hi> are put in one calamitous, ſuffering, bleeding, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, are yet quarrelling about their own opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, weakning the Proteſtant party by <hi>ſub-divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> which if united is ſcarce enough to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:125874:19"/>the common adverſary; ſhould this be if we had not loſt our peace with God? As the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> ſpeaks of the <hi>calamities</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Iuda,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 24.3. ſo may we ſay of the calamities up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Church of England, <hi>Surely at the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the Lord came this upon England;</hi> and the <hi>Lord grant,</hi> the <hi>Lord grant</hi> that the following words be not verified in their time, the Lord grant this be not <hi>come upon us, to remove England out of his ſight:</hi> but however we may take up the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches lamentation, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Thou haſt removed me far from peace; Ey, and as far from praiſe The crown is fallen from our head, Lam.</hi> 5.16. we are become a reproach to our neighbours, a ſcorn, a deriſion, a by-word, a ſhaking of the head; thoſe few of us that adhere to the Proteſtant Religion and cauſe, are repreſented to the world at home and abroad, as <hi>Sectaries, Anabaptiſts, Rebels,</hi> that if <hi>ever</hi> there were a <hi>time</hi> for us to cry to <hi>God</hi> to ſcatter thoſe clouds of <hi>bloud, confuſion, contempt,</hi> that cover the face of <hi>the Church,</hi> to bring forth our <hi>judgement</hi> as the <hi>light,</hi> and our <hi>righteouſneſſe as the morning,</hi> now is the time, <hi>Yee that are the Lords Remembrancers, keep no ſilence, give him no reſt, till he eſtabliſh, and till he make Ieruſalem a praiſe in the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A ſecond en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement of this duty from the perſons preſent.</note>And if ever <hi>Men</hi> were called to this work, we are called to it; 1 as <hi>Miniſters:</hi> 2 as <hi>Miniſters ſelected</hi> from the reſt of our brethren, <hi>to this preſent ſervice,</hi> whereunto we deſire to ſanctifie our ſelves this day. ½ As <hi>Miniſters</hi> it doth <hi>ex officio</hi> belong unto us, to be the Lords Remembrancers: to put the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:125874:19"/>Lord in mind of <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> you know what order the <hi>Lord</hi> took, that the <hi>Prieſts, the Miniſters of the Lord,</hi> under the Law, might continually remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>Iſrael</hi> the Church of God unto the Lord, the <hi>high Prieſt</hi> was to bear the names of the <hi>twelve tribes</hi> upon his <hi>ſhoulders,</hi> engraven in two ſtones; and upon his <hi>breaſt,</hi> engraven upon twelve ſtones: <hi>Ex.</hi> 28.12.29. <hi>that he might bear them upon his heart for a memoriall before the Lord continually;</hi> they were to be the <hi>Prieſts Remembrancers,</hi> that he ſhould be the <hi>Lords Remembrancer,</hi> to put the <hi>Prieſt in mind</hi> of putting <hi>God in mind</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by praying for them: this <hi>type</hi> is properly applyable to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is the <hi>only high Prieſt</hi> of his Church, yet ſo farre as the <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel</hi> are Chriſts ſubſtitutes upon earth, ſo farre this may (at leaſt by way of alluſion) be applyed unto them, for ſo farre there ought to be in them the ſame diſpoſition towards <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> that was in Chriſt <hi>Ieſus,</hi> that as <hi>Chriſt</hi> wept over <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ſo ſhould they; as he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ſo ſhould they; as he <hi>prayed for Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> ſo ſhould they; he by way of <hi>meritorious interceſsion,</hi> they by way of <hi>Miniſteriall interceſsion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.1.</note> to bear <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> upon their ſhoulders and upon their hearts continually, when ever they addreſſe themſelves into Gods preſence. <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven upon the <hi>hand of God,</hi> and therefore ſhould be <hi>ingrav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> upon the <hi>hearts</hi> of his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and is, if God hath layed his hand upon their hearts. Yee know the ſtory of that <hi>heathen Prieſt</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to offer ſacrifice before a battle writ <hi>Victoria</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:125874:20"/>(or ſome ſuch like word) in the palme of his hand, and in unbowelling the ſacrifice laid his hand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the heart of the beaſt, and left the characters of the ſame word there, that what had been writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten upon the <hi>hand</hi> of the <hi>Priest</hi> was read upon the <hi>heart</hi> of the <hi>ſacrifice. Behold I have graven thee, ſaith God to Ieruſalem, upon the palmes of my hands, Iſaiah</hi> 49.16. and look how many <hi>hearts</hi> there are of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> or <hi>Gentry,</hi> or <hi>Miniſters,</hi> or <hi>others,</hi> upon whom <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>layed his hand,</hi> I doubt not but there is the <hi>ſame configuration</hi> upon them that is <hi>ingraven</hi> upon the <hi>hand of God:</hi> that as <hi>God</hi> himſelfe <hi>cannot</hi> forget <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> (as he ſheweth there) <hi>becauſe it is engraven upon the palms of his hands;</hi> ſo <hi>they</hi> cannot but <hi>remember Ieruſalem,</hi> becauſe it is <hi>engraven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their hearts;</hi> that as Queen <hi>Mary</hi> ſaid of <hi>Callice,</hi> when I am dead rip me and you ſhall finde <hi>Callice at my heart:</hi> ſo there is a many a <hi>godly man,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a <hi>godly Miniſter</hi> eſpecially who might ſay, when I am dead rip me and you ſhall finde <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> at my heart. <hi>That ſacred name is deeply graven there; If I forget thee</hi> O Jeruſalem, <hi>let my right hand forget her cunning.</hi> All you that are the Lords <hi>Remembrancers,</hi> you that have <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> written in your <hi>hearts, keep no ſilence, give him no reſt, till he eſtabliſh, and till he make Ieruſalem a praiſe in the earth.</hi> If ever <hi>Men</hi> were called to this work, Miniſters are.</p>
            <p>And if ever <hi>Miniſters</hi> were called to this work, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more eſpecially are you whom it hath pleaſed <hi>God</hi> by the Authority of the <hi>honourable Houſes</hi> of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:125874:20"/>
               <hi>Parliament</hi> to call together to debate and adviſe of ſuch things as may be neceſſary, or conducing, to the eſtabliſhment of <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Beauty</hi> in the Churches of Chriſt Jeſus; and doth it not then eſpeciall lye upon you to <hi>keep no ſilence, give the Lord no reſt, till</hi> he <hi>eſtabliſh,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay <hi>till</hi> he <hi>eſtabliſh,</hi> for, <hi>except the Lord build the houſe, they labour in vain that build it;</hi> except the <hi>Lord reform</hi> the Church, it is to no <hi>purpoſe</hi> to goe about to <hi>reform</hi> it; except the Lord ſet up the Pillars of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> in his <hi>Church,</hi> and put the <hi>crown</hi> of <hi>Glory</hi> upon his <hi>Church,</hi> it is labour loſt to endevour it; You that are called to this great work, you of all men ought to <hi>keep no ſilence, give the Lord no reſt, till he eſtabliſh, and till he make Ieruſalem a praiſe in the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I need not tell you how many eies and expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions there are upon this <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> I ſpeak it not as a matter of boaſting, but as a matter of trembling and lying low before the <hi>Lord</hi> this day, from <hi>all</hi> the parts of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> from <hi>all</hi> the parts of the Chriſtian <hi>world,</hi> the eies of all the people of God are upon you; <hi>forrain Churches</hi> have their eies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, waiting what you will adviſe for the more utter <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>tinction of Papery,</hi> &amp; effecting of a more <hi>neer and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5+ letters">
                     <desc>•••••…</desc>
                  </gap>ion</hi> between us &amp; the reſt of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches; all</hi> the <hi>parts</hi> of the <hi>kingdome</hi> have their faces &amp; voyces towards you, me thinks I hear a voyce from all the corners of the Land comming up to this Aſſembly, to be by you reported to the honourable Houſes of Parliament; a voyce like that of the poore woman to the King upon the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:125874:21"/>wall, <hi>help, help,</hi> for the Lords ſake <hi>help: help us</hi> to better <hi>Miniſters,</hi> help us to better <hi>Ordinances,</hi> help us to purer <hi>worſhip,</hi> help us to better <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> help us to <hi>remove</hi> thoſe things that deterre us from the <hi>Lords table,</hi> help our tender Conſciences to more liberty, &amp;c. I know it <hi>Brethren,</hi> Gods people moſt of them look for help by this Aſſembly, through your faithfull advice given to the Honourable Houſes of Parliament. And may not you <hi>anſwer</hi> as he did there, <hi>except the Lord help thee, whence ſhould I help thee?</hi> there is ſuch an <hi>Augeae Stabulum</hi> of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, &amp; confuſion in Doctrine, Diſcipline, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, in all; that (verily) unleſſe <hi>that God</hi> who is able <hi>to remove the iniquity of the land in one day,</hi> Zach. 3.9. <hi>and to cauſe the Prophet &amp; unclean ſpirit to paſſe out of the land, Zach.</hi> 13.2. unleſſe that <hi>great God</hi> ſet his hand to this <hi>great work,</hi> it will never proſper; and yet if it ſhould not proſper, the ſin would be laid at your door, and you would bear the reproach of it to all memory; therefore great need to impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune God to come down and own his work; <hi>ô that thou wouldeſt rent the heavens and come down, that the Mountains might flow at thy preſence!</hi> Yee among all the reſt of <hi>the Lords Remembrancers, keep no ſilence, give him no reſt, till he eſtabliſh, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> make Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem a praiſe in the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ohe thing more, <hi>what</hi> I know you have all <hi>taught others</hi> your ſelves, now put in <hi>practice,</hi> purſue your <hi>prayers,</hi> with your <hi>indeavours;</hi> what yee <hi>pray for, contend for:</hi> as yee <hi>pray</hi> that God would <hi>eſtabliſh his Church in truth,</hi> ſo with <hi>united
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:125874:21"/>indeavours</hi> labour to raiſe up and <hi>eſtabliſh the</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed <hi>truth</hi> among us, vindicating the <hi>truths</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion from all <hi>Popiſh, Arminian, Socinian, Anabaptiſticall, Antinomian,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> other <hi>errors</hi> whatſoever. And as yee <hi>pray</hi> that <hi>God would eſtabliſh his Church in peace,</hi> ſo labour to <hi>work</hi> out the <hi>Churches peace;</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">1</hi> With <hi>God, by endeavouring</hi> a <hi>removall</hi> of what ever <hi>pollutions,</hi> or <hi>prophaneneſſes,</hi> have turned God into an enemy to us. And then <hi rend="sup">2</hi> 
               <hi>labour</hi> the <hi>Churches peace</hi> with its own mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; which certainly yee ſhall <hi>eſtabliſh,</hi> if <hi>denying</hi> your <hi>ſelves</hi> and laying by all pre-ingagements to your own opinions, deſires, ways, ye ſhall willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and unanimouſly, conſent to that which upon <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>pious</hi> debate ſhall be found to be the way and truth of <hi>God;</hi> which I doubt not but through his grace ye ſhall all doe. Beleeve it <hi>Brethren,</hi> in your Union will be laid a happy foundation of Union through the whole Kingdome; if yee agree in this <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> I durſt me thinks promiſe my ſelf, and you, a happy agreement amongſt all that fear God in the Nation: And then we need take no thought for the third thing, peace with our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: God will either ſubdue them under us, or make them be at peace with us: only let neither the deſire of peace with them, nor of peace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelves, bribe us <hi>to tolerate any thing in the Church of God that might make him to be at war with us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, as yee pray that God would make the Church a praiſe, ſo endeavour that alſo; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:125874:22"/>that the <hi>Church of Chriſt</hi> may enjoy all thoſe <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> that are <hi>purchaſed</hi> for her by <hi>the bloud,</hi> and <hi>bequeathed</hi> to her in <hi>the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament of her Lord Ieſus:</hi> that all her wayes may be <hi>ordered</hi> according to the <hi>rule</hi> of <hi>Gods word:</hi> that the <hi>Goſpell</hi> may runne and be <hi>glorifyed:</hi> that thoſe two <hi>great illuminating</hi> ordinances of <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>Catechizing,</hi> which are as the <hi>greater</hi> &amp; <hi>leſſer lights of heaven,</hi> may have ſuch <hi>liberty, encouragement, maintenance,</hi> that all the <hi>earth may be filled with the knowledge of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15.5.6.</note> This doe, and proſper: and that you may thus doe, <hi>the God of Patience and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation grant you to be like minded one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, according to</hi> Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>that you may with one mind and one mouth glorify God even the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Amen, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:125874:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
